Register of the Jerzy F. Karcz Papers, 1917-1970
Hoover Institution Archives
Jerzy F. Karcz Papers,
1917-1970
71028
Karcz, Jerzy F.
(40 manuscript boxes, 4 card file boxes, 1 phonotape (19 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, research notes, statistical surveys and reports, and miscellanea, relating to Soviet and East European agriculture and economics. Jerzy F. Karcz was also known as George Karcz.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1971.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Agriculture --Europe, Eastern; Agriculture --Soviet Union; Europe, Eastern; Europe, Eastern --Economic conditions; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union --Economic conditions; Economists; Phonotapes
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1931-1970. (Box 1)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1917-1970. (Boxes 1-33)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, lists, charts, notes, printed matter, xerox copies, etc., arranged alphabetically by subject.
- WRITINGS, 1930-1970. (Boxes 33-36)
  Handwritten and typewritten manuscripts, essays, etc., arranged alphabetically by title.
- MISCELLANEOUS. (Box 37)
  Clippings, miscellaneous, notes, charts, lists, etc.
- BIBLIOGRAPHICAL CARD FILE. (boxes 38-41)
  3x5 cards containing author, title, and subject reference to materials used for research.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1931-1970
  - Aldrich, Keith, 1964 (Box 1.)
  - Alexandre, R., 1968
  - Bergson, Abram, 1956-1957, 1968, 1970
  - Brooks, E. Willis, 1967
  - Bush, Keith, 1968
  - Byrnes, Robert F., 1966, 1968
  - Center for Research Libraries, 1970
  - Chapman, Janet, 1955-1956, 1970
  - Cheadle, Vernon I., 1968
  - Food Research Institute (Stanford University), 1931
  - Gerschenkron, Alexander, 1970
  - Goodrich, Carter
  - Goodrich, Professor, 1970
  - Horecky, Paul L.
  - Hooson, David, 1968
  - Jackson, Douglas, 1955
  - Kadlec, Vladimir (Minister of Education, Czechoslovakia), 1968
  - Karcz, Bart, 1970
  - Keldysh, M. V., 1968
  - Klatt, Werner, 1965-1966
  - Library of Congress, 1970
  - Lilienthal, Philip E., 1968
  - Nimitz, Nancy (Rand Corporation), 1955-1959
  - Nove, A., 1956
  - Popielovsky, Dimitry, 1968
  - Pryor, Frederic, 1969
  - Schultz, T. W., 1968
  - Smolenski, Jozef, 1958, 1969-1970
  - Smolinski, Leon, 1957-1958
  - Starovski, V. N., 1958
  - Timoshenko, V. P., 1963
  - Urban, George, 1969
  - Volin, Lazar, 1955
  - Vucinich, Wayne, 1965-1966
  - Wadekin, Karl-Eugen, 1968, 1970
  - Willett, Joseph W., 1963
  - Yelutin, V. P., 1968
  - Zaninovich, M. George, 1965
  - Zauberman, Alfred, 1969
  - Miscellaneous
- SUBJECT FILES, 1917-1970
  - "Abbreviations for Price Handbooks Used in Rand Studies of the Prices of Soviet Basic Industrial Goods," by Abram Bergson, 1955 (Box 1.)
  - Agriculture
  - "Agriculture in the Industrialization of Communist China and the Soviet Union," by Anthony Tang, 1967
  - "Agriculture in the Industrialization of Communist China and the Soviet Union: A Comment," Nancy Nimitz (Rand Corporation), 1967
  - Agricultural Development Council, Inc.
    - "Economic Meaning of Subsistance," by C. R. Wharton, 1963
    - "Micro-Development: The Transformation of Village Level Economies," by C. R. Wharton, 1968
    - "Selected Bibliography for Conference on Subsistence and Peasant Economies," by C. R. Wharton, 1964
  - "Agricultural Marketing and Economic Development," by William O. Jones, 1970
  - "The Agricultural Situation in Communist Areas," U.S. Department of Agriculture. Economic Research Service, 1969/1970
  - American Association of Teachers of Slavic and East European Languages. Bulletin. 1951: Vol. IX, No. 1.
  - Association for Comparative Economics (Box 2.)
    - General
    - Proceedings of National Association for Comparative Economics Meetings. San Francisco, California, December 27-29, 1969
  - Association for the Study of Soviet-Type Economics
  - Association of Economists Working on the USSR and Eastern Europe
  - Bibliography of Anthropological and Sociological Publications on Eastern Europe and the USSR
  - Bills and invoices
  - Bulgaria
    - General
    - Agriculture
    - Agriculture and economy
    - Agriculture and economy (Box 3.)
    - "The Auxiliary Plot of the Cooperative Farmers," 1963
    - Economy
    - Employment and labor (Box 4.)
    - Labor and population
    - Livestock
    - Population
    - Sources
    - Statistics
  - "Capital Theory and Development Planning," by R. F. Findlay
  - China
    - General
    - Agriculture and industry
    - "Input-Output Relations in the Agriculture of Communist China," by Anthony Tang
  - "Chinese and Soviet Transport for Agriculture, by Holland Hunter
  - Communist economic offensive
  - Communist social systems
  - "A Comparison of Retail Prices in the US, USSR and Western Europe," by Keith Bush, 1967
  - Conference on the Economic Development of European Socialist Countries. Plovdiv, Bulgaria. Nov.-Dec. 1964 (Box 5.)
  - Conference on the Role of Agriculture in Economic Development. Princeton, New Jersey. December 1967
    - "Agricultural Planning: The Peruvian Experience," by H. Van de Wetering (Iowa State University)
    - "Agriculture in the Open Economy," by John C. Rei and Gustav Ranis (Cornell and Yale Universities)
    - Attendance
    - "Notes Toward a Multi-Regional Model of World Economic Development Emphasizing Agriculture," by Karl A. Fox (Iowa State University)
    - "A Programming Model for a Dual Economy," by J. Sandee (Netherlands School of Economics)
    - "Prospects for LDC's Agricultural Trade," by Louis Marie Goreux (IBRD)
    - "Quantitative and Policy Relationships between Agriculture, Non-Agriculture and Foreign Trade Throughout the Growth Process: The Case of Argentina and Peru," by Erik Thorbecke (Agency for International Development) and Alfred Field (University of North Carolina)
    - "A Regional Model for Agricultural Development," by Alan Brown (University of Bristol)
    - "The Transformation of Agriculture in a Semi-Industrialized Country: The Case of Brazil," by William H. Nicholls (Vanderbilt University)
  - "Contemporary Economic Systems and the Teleological Conception of the State," by Karel Holbik
  - Council of Mutual Assistance
  - Czechoslovakia
    - General
    - Agriculture and economy
    - "Bureaucracy and the Interest Groups in Communist Societies: The Case of Czechoslovakia," by Andrzej Korbonski
    - "Czechoslovak Economic Reform as a Process of Socialist Resolution," by O. Turek
    - "Czechoslovakia in December 1968," by Andrzej Korbonski
    - "Czechoslovakia's New Political Model: A Preliminary Assessment," by Morton Schwartz
    - Economy (Box 6.)
    - Finances, 1965
    - Food comsumption, 1942
    - "The Performance of Socialist Agriculture," by Gregor Lazacik (Columbia University), 1963
    - Radio Free Europe, 1970
    - "Was Edward Benes Guilty?" by Ferdinand Peroutka
  - "Democracy and Socialism," by Professor Howard J. Sherman
  - Development and technology
  - "East European Foreign Trade Data Bank: An Interim Report," by Paul Marer, June 1970
  - Eastern Europe
    - General
    - Agriculture
    - Agriculture and economy
    - Agriculture and industry (Box 7.)
    - "Food Balances for 8 East European Countries, 1959-1961"
    - Food comsumption
    - Geography, 1969
    - Industry
    - Population
    - "The Warsaw Fall of 1956 and the Prague Spring of 1968: A Preliminary Comparison," by Andrzej Korbonski
  - Eastern European Economics. 1969: Vol. VII, No. 3 (Spring)
  - Economic backwardness
  - Economic development
  - Economic theory
  - "The Economics of Nationalism," by Albert Breton
  - Economics
  - Economics (Box 8.)
  - Economics (Box 9.)
  - "Economies and Diseconomies of Large-Scale Agriculture," by Philip M. Raup, 1969
  - Europe. Agriculture and economy
  - "The Europe and Soviet Union Agricultural Situation," U.S. Department of Agriculture. Economic Research Service. 1968
  - Far Western Slavic Conference, USC. May 1-2, 1970
  - Food-Calorie Disappearance Per Capita Among European Nations in Peacetime
  - "From Stalin to Brezhnev: The Soviet Rural Community in Economic Historical Perspective."
  - "Government and Business in International Trade," by Heinrich Kronstein
  - Government and economic development
  - Grain Bulletin, 1968: Vol. XIV, No. 2 (February)
  - Grain production in Europe, 1933-1941
  - Hungary
    - General
    - Agriculture
    - Agriculture and economy
    - Economy
    - Economy (Box 10.)
    - "The Historical Background to Hungarian Agriculture," by Lewis A. Fischer and P. E. Uren
  - India
    - "Ideology and Politics in Economic Planning: The problem of Indian Agricultural Development Strategy," by Francine R. Frankel
    - "The Pricing of Food in India," by Ali M. Khusro
  - Indiana University. Inter-University Conference on Graduate Study in the Soviet Union. August 13-14, 1960
  - "Industrialization and Peasantry: An Economists' View," by Andrzej Brzeski
  - Inflation
  - International agencies
  - International income
  - International trade
  - Japan
  - Kenya (Box 11.)
  - Land reform
  - Marxist development model
  - Meat and Dairy Produce Bulletin, 1968: Vol. XXI, No. 8 (August)
  - Mexico
    - Agriculture
    - "Ideology and Economic Development in Mexico," by Clark W. Reynolds (Food Research Institute, Stanford Univeristy)
    - "Work Patterns in a Mayo Village," by Charles J. Erasmus
  - "National-International Linkages: France and China as Non-Conforming Alliance Members," by Ole R. Holsti and John D. Sullivan
  - "Notes on a Trip to Russia and Poland (May-June 1959), by Herbert S. Levine
  - "Notes on Interviews in the Soviet Union by Six American Economists."
  - "On Monocentric and Polycentric Planning," by R. Bicanic
  - "On the Description and Comparison of Economic Systems," by Tjalling C. Koopmens and John Michael Montias
  - Philippine Islands
    - "Price and Market Relationships for Rice and Corn in the Philippines," by Mahar Mangahas, Aida E. Recto, and V. W. Ruttan
  - "The Planner and the Politician," by Rudolf Bicani c. 1966
  - Poland
    - General
    - Agriculture and economy (Box 12.)
    - Economy, 1930-1939
    - "Polish Discussion on Socialist Transformation in Agriculture," by Jerzy Tepicht
  - Population
  - "Profit, Supply and Factor Demand Functions with Application to Indian Agriculture," by Lawrence J. Lau and Pan A. Yotopoulos, 1970
  - "Recent Thought on Egalitarianism," by Robert J. Lampman
  - Reference cards, lists, sources, etc.
  - Reference cards, lists, sources, etc. (Box 13.)
  - Regional Development Processes in Southeast Europe: A Comparative Analysis of Bulgaria and Greece," by George W. Hoffman
  - Research Conference on Economic Reform in Eastern Europe. University of Michigan. November 1970
    - Program
    - "Concentration and Efficiency in Eastern European Reforms," by Michael Keren
    - "Decentralizing the Command Economy: The Study of a Pragmatic Strategy for Reformers," by T. A. Marschak
    - "The Firm in the New Economic Mechanism in Hungary," by Bela Balassa
    - "Foreign Trade in the East European Reforms," by Alan A. Brown and Paul Marer
    - "Planning and the Market in the Czechoslovak Reform," by Vaclav Holesovsky
    - "Planning and the Market in Yugoslavia," by S. Pejovich
    - "The Political Implications of Economic Reform," by R. V. Burks (Box 14.)
    - "The Politics of Economic Reform in Bulargia and Rumania," by R. V. Burks
    - "The Strategy of Economic Reforms," by Richard D. Portes
  - "Resource Allocation and Rural-Urban Interactions in Developing Economies," by John B. Cownie and Scott R. Pearson
  - "Risk, Uncertainty, and the Subsistence Farmer: Technological Innovation and Resistance to Change in the Context of Survival," by Clifton J. Wharton
  - Rumania
    - General
    - Agriculture
  - Schumpeter model
  - Selected Congressional References on Soviet, East European and Communist Chinese Affairs, 1968
  - "The Smallholder in Tropical Export Crop Production," by V. D. Wickizer
  - South America
    - Agrarian reform and peasantry
  - Soviet and other communist graduate student exchange programs
  - Statistical handbooks published in the USSR, May 1958
  - Statistics
  - "Student Morality: From Skepticism to Dogmatism," by Arthur Danto (Box 15.)
  - Subsistence and peasant economies
  - Sudetenland. Crops and livestock, 1938
  - Sweden
  - Tax policies
  - Teaching aids, notes, etc.
  - Timoshenko, V. P. (Box 16.)
  - "Toward a Beter Understanding of the Issues: Capitalism, Socialism, Communism, and Industrialism," by Garrett D. Connelly
  - "Toward the Study of National-International Linkages," by James N. Roseneau
  - Ukraine. Statistics
  - Underdeveloped countries
  - USSR
    - General
    - "Agricultural Administration in Russia from the Stolypin Land Reform to Forced Collectivization: An Interpretive Study," by George L. Yaney
    - Agriculture
    - Agriculture (Box 17.)
    - Agriculture and economy (Box 18.)
    - Agriculture and economy (Box 19.)
    - Agriculture and livestock
    - "Agriculture and Structural Transformation in a Developing Economy," by Bruce F. Johnson and Soren T. Nielsen
    - "Agriculture Under Khrushchev: The Lean Years," by Nancy Nimitz (Rand Corporation), March 1965
    - "American Tractors and Early Soviet Agriculture," by Dana G. Dalrymple
    - "Are We Flirting with Capitalism?" by Yevsei Liberman (Kharkov State University)
    - Banks
    - Bukharin, Nikolai Ivanovich
    - "Climatic and Crop Analysis for the Soviet Union: A Study of the Possibilities of Increasing Grain Yields," by D. Gale Johnson, 1957
    - Collective farm income
    - Collective farm management
    - Collective farm market
    - Collective farm market prices
    - Collective farm market sales (Box 20.)
    - "Collectivization and Economic Development," by Z. M. Fallenbuchl
    - Consumer goods
    - "Continuity and Change in the Administration of Soviet Agriculture Since Stalin," by Robert F. Miller
    - Cotton
    - "Development Strategy and Planning: The Soviet Experience," - Comments by Abram Bergson
    - Economy
    - Economy (Box 21.)
    - Economy (Box 22.)
    - "Effects of Industrialization on Political Institutions in the USSR, 1930-1960," by David T. Cattell
    - Eggs
    - "The Eighth and Ninth Five-Year Plans for Soviet Agriculture," by Keith Bush
    - Employment and labor
    - "Engineers or Martyrs: Dissent and the Intelligentsia," by Sidney Monas
    - Famine of 1932-1934
    - Farm marketings
    - Farm prices (Box 23.)
    - "Feeding of the Russian Worker before and after the War," by E. Kabo
    - "The First 10 Years of the Virgin Lands: A Balance Sheet."
    - Five-Years Plans
    - Flax fiber market
    - From the book Europe in the Russian Mirror by Alexander Gerschenkron
    - Fruit, tobacco and vegetables
    - Grain
    - Grain (Box 24.)
    - Grain (Box 25.)
    - Grain harvests, 1926
    - Grain market in European Russia, 1912
    - "Group Politics in Communist Society: A Second Look at the Pluralistic Model," by Andrew C. Janos
    - History
    - History (Box 26.)
    - "The Importance of Religion in the Soviet Rural Community," by Ethel Dunn
    - Income, state
    - "The Incomes of Soviet Peasants," by A. Nove
    - Industry
    - International Association of Agricultural Economists. Minsk. August -September 1970
    - Kazakhstan
    - Kolkhozes
    - Kolkhozes (Box 27.)
    - "Khrushchev Sans Reproche," by Nancy Nimitz (Rand Corporation), January 1966
    - Legal literature on agriculture in the USSR
    - Livestock
    - "Local Government and Decentralization," by Bohdan R. Bockiurkiw
    - Machinery output, 1927-1928, 1937
    - Makhorka
    - Marketings
    - Meat
    - Milk and milk products
    - "The Non-Agricultural Rural Sector: Expanding in a Shrinking Society," by Karl-Eugen Wadekin (Box 28.)
    - "Notes on Visit of American Agricultural Delegation to USSR," by D. Gale Johnson, 1955
    - Oil seeds
    - "Organizational Change in Soviet Bloc: An Essay on Political Economy of Socialism," by Andrzej Brzeski, 1966
    - "The Other Russia: Soviet Rural Society," by Martin King Whyte, 1967
    - "The Peasants as a Social Class," by Alexander Vucinich, 1969
    - "Planning a Mature Economy in the USSR," by R. W. Davies
    - "Planning and Productivity under Soviet Socialism," by Abram Bergson
    - Political structure
    - "La Politique Aricole de Leonid Brezhnev, 1965-1970," by Alec Nove
    - Population
    - Potato market
    - Price data
    - Price lists
    - Price lists (Box 29.)
    - "Problems of State Farm Administration," by Allen B. Ballard, 1964
    - Procurement prices
    - "Progress on Mechanization in Soviet Agriculture," by Folke Dovring
    - "A Reformulation of A. V. Chayanov's Theory of the Peasant Economy," by James R. Millar
    - "The R.S.F.S.R. and the Non-Russian Republics: An Economic Comparison by Hans-Jurgen Wagener
    - "Rural Population and Agricultural Labor Force in the USSR," by Alexandre N. Sakoff
    - "Rural Reconstruction and the Agrogorod," by Karl-Eugen Wadekin (Radio Liberty Committee), 1968
    - "Russian Report: March/April, 1969," by A. Nove
    - "School Enrollment in the USSR, 1970-75," (CIA)
    - "Sino-Soviet Economic Relations in Recent Years," by Oleg Hoeffding, (Rand Corporation), 1960
    - "Some Characteristics of the Soviet Leadership System: A Maturing Totalitarian System," by Roy D. Laird
    - "Some Evidence on Soviet Agricultural Marketings," by Leon Smolinski
    - "Some Observations on the Impact of Politics on Soviet Agriculture," by Roy D. Laird, 1968
    - "Some Thoughts on Soviet Agricultural Administration," by Alec Nove, 1964
    - "Soviet Collectivization and China's 'Great Leap,'" by Oleg Hoeffding, 1965
    - "The Soviet Economic Reform After 5 years," by Keith Bush
    - "Soviet Farm Output and Food Supply in 1970: An Assessment," by Werner Klatt
    - "Soviet Foreign Trade and the 'Grain Problem' During NEP." (Box 30)
    - "Soviet Foreign Trade Crisis and Soviet Economic Autarky in the 1930's."
    - "Soviet Foreign Trade Plans for the First Five Year Plan and Soviet Industrialization Strategy, 1928-1932," by Michael R. Dohan, 1969
    - "Soviet Growth, Resource Allocation, and Military Outlays," by Abraham S. Becker, 1969
    - "Soviet Living Standards," by P. Hanson
    - "The Soviet Planning Process for Rapid Industrialization," by R. W. Davies
    - "Stalin, War Communism and Collectivization," by O. A. Narkiewicz
    - State procurement prices, 1926-1938
    - State procurements
    - Statistics
    - Statistics (Box 31.)
    - Statistics (Box 32.)
    - "Structure and Functions of the Soviet Rural Family," by Stephen P. Dunn
    - "Study of Soviet Economic Growth and Working Memorandum on Russian Budget Studies," by Nancy Baster (National Bureau of Economic Research), 1955
    - Sugar beet market
    - Sunflowers
    - Tobacco market
    - Tractors and cultivation
    - Trade
    - Vegetable market
    - Vegetables and melons, 1935-1937
    - Weights
    - Wool (Box 33.)
  - United States of America
    - Agriculture
    - Consumer Sector, 1953
    - Economy
    - Foreign aid
    - Government agencies
    - Income tax, 1958
  - "U.S. Malinvestments in Food for the World," by Theodore W. Schultz, 1966
  - Western Europe
    - Agriculture
    - "The New Economics of Western Europe," by Philip M. Raup, 1967
  - "World Economic Disparities: The Haves and Have-Nots," by David Horowitz
  - World military expenditures, 1966-1967
  - Yugoslavia
    - General
    - Agriculture
    - Economy
    - "The Emergence of Regional Spatial Planning in Southeast Europe: the Yugoslav Experience," by Jack C. Fisher
    - "Major Trends in the Post-War Economy of Yugoslavia," by George Macesich, 1965
- WRITINGS
  - Agricultural Reform in Eastern Europe (Box 33.)
  - Agriculture and the Economics of Soviet Development
  - Agriculture and the Economics of Soviet Development (Box 34.)
  - Agriculture and the Industrialization of Ruritania
  - Certain Aspects of New Economic Systems in Bulgaria and Czechoslovakia
  - A Compendium of Soviet Farm Prices in 1961
  - The Economic Record of Soviet Agriculture at Mid-Century Point
  - Estimates of Extra-Village Collective Farm Market Prices and Volume of Sales for the USSR, 1940, 1950-1961
  - The Flow of Funds Accounts
  - From Stalin to Brezhnev: Soviet Agricultural Policy in Historical Perspective
  - From Stalin to Brezhnev: The Soviet Rural Community in Economic Historical Perspective
  - General Framework of National Income Statictics (Box 35.)
  - Government Borrowing
  - Government Spending
  - Investment
  - Khrushchev's Impact on Soviet Agriculture
  - Quantitative Analysis of the Collective Farm Market
  - Reflections on the Economics of Nationalism and Communism in Eastern Europe
  - Sector Accounts
  - Soviet Agricultural Marketings and Prices, 1928-1954
  - Soivet Agricultural Policy after Khrushchev
  - Soviet Agricultural Policy Since 1953
  - Soviet Agriculture: A Balance Sheet
  - Soivet Farm Prices, 1928-1952
  - Soivet Farm Prices under Stalin
  - Statistical Quality Control
  - Thoughts on the Grain Problem
  - Thoughts on the Grain Problem (Box 36.)
  - Appendices
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes
- MISCELLANEOUS
  - Clippings (Box 37.)
  - Miscellaneous notes, manuscripts, printed material, etc.
- BIBLIOGRAPHICAL CARD FILE
  - 3x5 cards containing author, title, and subject references to materials used in G. F. Karczs' research (Box 38-41.)